Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna,
and this is Geshe Michael Roach,
and this is our third course
covering a very, very famous book.
Maybe it's the most famous
Buddhist book after the Buddha,
and it's just called "Wisdom."
And it's by someone that
we call Arya Nagarjuna.
Arya of course means that
he saw emptiness directly.
And in fact, he's so famous
as a emptiness direct seer
that sometimes he's just called The Arya.
He lived almost exactly 2000 years ago.
And I think there may be
some interesting connections
between some Christian
saints: Thomas the disciple
who came to India and Nagarjuna.
And he really took the
Buddhist teachings on emptiness
after 700 years, and he really,
really woke them up again.
I think one of the
signs that he's an Arya,
number one is he's funny
and he's just really clever
and funny when he presents things.
Secondly, he really
enjoyed writing in poetry,
and he's very, very simple.
So I think that's also a sign
that he really did see emptiness directly.
He prefers to speak very
simply, very clearly.
It's almost like he's
singing a song when he wrote
his greatest book of all is
called, just simply, "Wisdom".
In Sanskrit, which we're
going to talk about later,
it's called Prajna.
I think that's another sign he's an Arya:
he just named his book "Wisdom."
And later people would say,
the root text on "Wisdom",
or Mūla madhyamaka kārikā,
the verses of the root text on wisdom.
But Nargajuna himself
preferred to call his book
just "Wisdom". How can we see emptiness?
How can I help you to see emptiness?
And that little book, 27
tiny chapters in poetry,
became, you know, for 2000 years,
hundreds of commentaries were written
about these simple 27 small verses.
And it really, all the emptiness teachings
that you've ever heard,
that I've ever heard,
all the emptiness
teachings in Tibet, China,
Korea, Japan, they're all
based on Nagarjuna's "Wisdom".
So I thought, about three years ago,
I was thinking it would
be a really nice break
during the Lam Rim if
we studied for dessert,
if we studied Arya Nagarjuna's "Wisdom".
And recently we've been doing
Medicine Buddha practices,
especially because of the virus,
and I thought it would
be really, really cool
if we connected Arya Nagarjuna's "Wisdom"
and the practice of Medicine Buddha.
I personally feel strongly
that if you don't understand
the emptiness of the
Medicine Buddha practice,
Medicine Buddha himself,
and the emptiness of the
mantra of the Medicine Buddha,
then I don't think it will work so strong.
It will work a little bit.
The mantras will work a little bit
and all the different practices
like meditation, retreat,
saving the lives of animals,
these are all powerful practices.
But if you really understand the emptiness
of these practices, if you
understand the emptiness
of saving someone's life, or
you understand the emptiness
of speaking of a mantra,
then in my opinion,
the practice is a thousand
times more powerful.
So we're going to go
through Nagarjuna's "Wisdom" together.
Then from time to time,
we'll try to connect it
to the Medicine Buddha
practice and supercharge,
put an engine, extra booster,
rocket booster on your
Medicine Buddha practice.
My plan was to go through the
"Wisdom" text, 27 chapters,
in five years, probably
the greatest commentary
of many, many great
commentaries, for example,
by Chandrakirti,
Buddhapalita, Bhavaviveka,
these great, great ancient
Indian commentaries.
And then Tsongkapa came
along, I don't know,
1,200 years after Arya Nargajuna
and he wrote a book called
"The Sea of Emptiness,"
"The Ocean of Emptiness."
And that's a great, great
commentary on the 27 verses.
And then even Tsongkapa is very difficult.
After that Choney Lama Drakpa Shedrup
about 200, 300 years after Tsongkapa,
he wrote a funny book called,
"A Ship to Travel Across
the Sea of Emptiness".
It means Tsongkapa's, even
Tsongkapa's commentary's
too difficult.
And we need like, Choney
Lama gives us a boat,
so we don't drown in Tsongkapa's book.
So we're going to be going through
Choney Lama's explanation.
I'll be using that.
And I'm translating it as we go.
It's very difficult.
The verses are very, very difficult.
Without Choney Lama I don't think we could
understand Nagarjuna correctly.
And so here we go.
We're going to first review,
this first class is a review
of the chapters that we finished already.
We did finish the first eight chapters
of Nagarjuna's "Wisdom".
And we're going to just
go through those today,
in this class, we'll go
through those eight chapters
and just review them together.
The first chapter is called,
"An Investigation of Conditions".
Each of the 27 chapters
is called pariksha.
Pariksha means an investigation,
or an examination,
or an analysis of a certain topic.
So Nagarjuna will take a certain idea
and in the first case here
we're talking about causes.
What causes something else?
How does a seed work to cause a tree?
So that's the first chapter, the pariksha,
the examination or the investigation.
And it feels like a Sherlock
Holmes investigation.
How does this really work?
How do seeds really create
trees and how do mantras
of Medicine Buddha cure a
disease to cure a sickness?
How does it really work?
How do conditions work?
And in this first chapter,
Nargajuna goes through the
four classic conditions
that are presented in the
Abhidharma before Nargajuna,
before Nargajuna came.
So he's looking into causes.
How does a mantra cure a disease
in the Medicine Buddha case?
How does a tree seed really create a tree?
And this is the pariksha.
This is the first examination.
The most famous lines of
"Wisdom" are found here.
Actually, it's not even the first chapter.
It's the traditional prostration
at the beginning of a book.
So it's tradition to bow down
at the beginning of a great
Buddhist commentary, a great,
great Buddhist book, shastra
or sutra. You bow down to your teacher,
or you bow down to some holy object.
And what Nargajuna chooses to
bow down to is always a sign
of what he's going to be
talking about for 27 chapters.
Who does he choose to bow
down to at the beginning
of his book. And that verse, those verses,
those lines of his first bowing down
at the beginning of the book,
these are the most
famous lines by Nargajuna
and probably the most famous
lines ever about emptiness.
So if you wanted to memorize them,
this would be a good thing to memorize.
Now what's the topic that as he bows down?
By the way, I'm going to
recite the lines for you.
,GANG GIS RTEN CING 'BREL BAR 'BYUNG,
,'GAG PA MED PA SKYE MED PA,
,CHAD PA MED PA RTAG MED PA,
,'ONG BA MED PA 'GRO MED PA,
,THA DAD DON MIN DON GCIG MIN,
,SPROS PA NYER ZHI ZHI BSTAN PA,
,RDZOGS PA'I SANGS RGYAS SMRA RNAMS KYI,
,DAM PA DE LA PHYAG 'TSAL LO,,
Okay, he bows down to the Buddha.
And it's very, very interesting.
He starts out this first verse with GANG.
And in Sanskrit it's yah.
And it's kind of famous
way to start a verse,
and it's kind of a guessing game.
He goes, "I'm thinking of somebody",
and then he describes the person,
and then you're supposed
to guess who's this person.
You see, that's a
traditional Sanskrit stotra,
or a praise of somebody,
singing someone's praises.
I'm thinking of the most
beautiful lady in the world.
Some blonde hair, and
brown eyes, and so sweet.
Guess who I'm talking about?
Then you're supposed to
guess who he's talking about.
So these two verses,
two shlokas in Sanskrit,
they are the most famous verses,
probably, about emptiness,
of ever, of ever.
And let's go through the meaning of them.
Let's talk about... let's
break down the meaning
of the Sanskrit,sorry, the Tibetan.
We can do the Sanskrit sometime.
GANG GIS RTEN CING 'BREL BAR 'BYUNG
I'm thinking of somebody who was teaching
about the idea that things
happen from other things.
If this happens, that happens.
If the seed is there and it
gets wet, it will grow a tree.
And if this mantra, if this
Medicine Buddha mantra is here
and it's done correctly,
then it could cure disease,
or it could bring
someone to enlightenment.
You see?
So he's thinking somebody taught
us how things really work,
because the whole topic of this book
is that things don't
work the way you think.
Things don't work the
way you think, right?
And I don't know, I have a garden.
It's time to plant some flowers.
I put the seeds in the ground.
I water them.
I put biochar on all my plants.
And then sometimes they grow
and then sometimes they don't grow at all.
Recently I planted three peach trees
and two of them are in very good soil.
They have good water, no stones.
They didn't grow so well.
One of them is in rocky soil.
It's out in the middle of... you know,
it shouldn't grow, but that one grew.
So it means that something's going on.
It means that the things we
think are causes are not causes,
and things we don't think
are causes are really causes.
And I will say, things
that we think cause things,
don't cause things, sorry, and things
that we didn't think cause
things do cause things.
GANG GIS RTEN CING 'BREL BAR 'BYUNG
Then he goes into something called,
and it's very important for our review:
"The eight impossibles",
eight different impossibles.
Eight things are impossible.
For example, a seed cannot grow a tree.
That's impossible.
A mantra cannot heal a disease.
Not possible.
There are three, sorry, there
are eight kinds of impossible.
And in his first bowing
down to the Buddha,
Arya Nargajuna gives
us the us those eight.
So here they are:
'GAG PA MED PA, nothing
stops the way you think.
The disease doesn't stop from
the mantra, the way you think.
SKYE MED PA, your understanding
from saying the mantra, it
doesn't come the way you think.
CHAD PA MED PA RTAG MED
PA, things don't stop.
Things aren't cut off and
things don't continue over time
in the way you think they do.
'ONG BA MED PA 'GRO MED
PA, even when you go
to sit down on your meditation cushion
and then you do your mantras and you get
up from your meditation cushion,
the way you sit on the
cushion and the way you
get up off the cushion to do
your Medicine Buddha mantras,
even that's not what
you think is going on.
If you don't even know
how you're sitting down,
how are you going to understand
how to do the mantras?
Much more complicated.
Even when you put your
bottom on the cushion,
you don't really know what's happening.
And so if you sit on the
cushion and do mantras
how you are going to
know what's happening?
So you have to understand
the emptiness of the mantra,
the emptiness of the Medicine Buddha,
and the emptiness of sitting
down and standing up.
'ONG BA MED PA 'GRO MED PA,
THA DAD DON MIN DON GCIG MIN,
Things are not separate from each other.
I'm not separate from
the camera right now.
But I'm also not not separate.
I'm not separate, but
I'm not not separate.
What does that mean?
Is the seed separate from the tree?
Is the mantra of Medicine Buddha separate
from curing disease, or
reaching enlightenment?
Are they separate, or
are they the same thing?
If they're separate, do they touch?
If they're the same thing, then why do you
have to do the mantra, because
it's already enlightenment?
So that's a big question.
SPROS PA NYER ZHI ZHI BSTAN PA
SPROS PA here means we tend
to project our wrong
ideas onto other people.
The big example is the
husband in the kitchen.
We come home from a hard day at work.
We walk in the kitchen peacefully.
We don't want to fight. And then suddenly
the husband starts acting
strange, and saying things.
Then you're like, "Wow,
I didn't do anything,
"and he seems unhappy at me today,
"but I didn't do anything".
So that's an example of SPROS PA.
SPROS PA means you're making up a story
about your husband,
that you didn't do anything.
That's called SPROS PA.
A story that you made
up about your husband.
The truth is, as you know the story,
you yelled at your kids last week, right?
You did something last week.
But you made up a story
about your husband.
That's called SPROS PA.
SPROS PA NYER ZHI ZHI BSTAN PA
Nargajuna says, "This person
that I'm thinking of", who
he hasn't identified yet,
"I'm thinking of a
person who taught us how
"to shut down those fake stories
"about your husband, or your wife."
There's something who taught us shanti,
how to get to the peace
which is shutting down your stupid stories
about your husband.
RDZOGS PA'I SANGS RGYAS, and then finally,
in the second half of the second verse,
he says, "Guess what?
I'll tell you who it was."
RDZOGS PA'I SANGS RGYAS
SMRA RNAMS KYI DAM PA
the totally enlightened Buddha,
who is the highest of all teachers.
That's who it was.
That's who it was who taught us
how seeds really make trees,
who taught us why husbands are yelling,
who taught us why Medicine
Buddha mantras work.
This is the - dan-da-da-da! -
the fully enlightened Buddha,
the greatest of teachers,
SMRA RNAMS KYI DAM PA.
And then DE LA PHYAG 'TSAL LO
I bow down to this teacher.
The English translation and
English order will be reversed.
I bow down to that highest of teachers,
to the fully enlightened
one who teaches us
to reach that peace, where our fantasies
about how things exist
are put to a final rest.
I bow down to the one who taught us
that things happen in dependence:
nothing ends, nothing
begins, nothing stops,
but nothing ever lasts forever,
nothing comes and nothing goes.
No two things are different,
nor are any two the same.
So there's the beginning of the book.
If you're going to die today,
at least you heard the most
important part of the book.
That's the first verse.
And really, if you have
time, you should memorize it
in your own language maybe.
And by the way, it doesn't
matter what language it is.
The important thing is to learn it
and have it singing in your head.
All right. Then let's go
through those eight impossibles quickly.
Here's the first idim.
Here's the first picture.
Nothing can end.
If you do do Medicine Buddha mantras,
don't expect your physical problems,
or those of your loved ones
to end, because nothing ends.
It's not possible for something
to end because you did mantras.
Now that sounds very negative.
It sounds like Geshe-la's telling you
just forget doing mantras. It's not that.
The way you think the
mantra works is wrong.
And if the way you think
about the mantra, how it works
is wrong, it will affect
how the mantra works.
Will the mantra work on its own?
To some extent the mantra has a power.
But if you understand how it
works, it will really work.
So first of all, and
it's very interesting,
there's a big debate.
Nargajuna doesn't say nothing
starts and nothing stops.
He says nothing stops and nothing starts.
And there's a big argument
why he starts with stopping,
instead of starting with starting.
You guys have to think about it.
For some reason, he's in
the mood of negatives.
You got the clue? It's emptiness.
Something's not there.
Stop thinking like that
and then you can start
thinking like that, okay?
Then he talks about how things can begin
and like that, how they
couldn't last forever,
how they could come, how they could go.
That's pretty much a summary
of the first chapter.
And again to teach this book carefully
would take about 20 years.
So we're going to try to jump
across the river on
stones of the main ideas.
Second chapter is called
"An Investigation of Going and Coming",
'GRO 'ONG GI BRTAG PA in Tibetan.
And the theme is: look, if there's no me
and there's no mine, then
who comes into this life
and who goes to the next life?
If there's no me, then
who came into this life
and who goes out in this life?
Who goes to the next life?
So the second chapter is an investigation
of if there's... According
to the opening lines,
there's no coming, there's no going.
Well then, who comes into this life
and who goes out of this life?
And as you may remember, and by the way,
I encourage you to go back and
look at the earlier segments
on The Knowledge Base, probably?
If you weren't there for
the first eight chapters,
then I really encourage
you to look at the videos
for the first eight chapters
because this book is deep.
And if you don't have a good foundation
in the earlier chapters,
you're going to have trouble
in the later chapters.
You're going to have trouble
in the first chapters
with all the preparation,
but you're going to have more
trouble if you don't prepare.
And those of you will remember
that we were talking about,
the whole discussion in
chapter two was based
on three parts of a path.
And we'll show a picture
here of walking, right?
Walking along a path.
And there's this idea that
there's a part of the path
that you already walked on,
and there's a part of the path
that you're going to walk on,
and then there's a part of the path
between those two where
you are stepping now.
So how long is the part
you already walked on
and how long is the part
you're going to walk on,
and how big is the part
you're walking on now?
Maybe it's so thin that it's not there.
Where's the line between
where you already step
and where you're going to step?
How big is that line?
And you're like, "Geshe-la, who cares?"
Right? who cares?
Well, you're going to to be doing mantras
for Medicine Buddha, right?
You're going to start the
mantra: om, you guys say, om.
And then you're going to say
sva ha or something at the end.
And you said there's going
to be a start to the mantra,
a part of the mantra you already said,
and there's a part of the
mantra you didn't say yet,
mantra that you're saying now,
but it can't exist without
the start of the mantra
and the end of the mantra.
But the start of the
mantra stopped already,
and the end of the mantra hasn't come yet.
If the mantra that
you're saying is halfway
between those two, and
one of them doesn't exist
or both of them don't exist,
well, how can you be saying a mantra?
So that was chapter two.
If you can not answer
that question right now,
go study chapter two again.
Let's look at chapter three.
And this was our... by the way,
the first two chapters we covered
in the first Nargajuna
course. And then now
here's the second Nargajuna
course that we did.
Then after that we're
going to start this course,
which is course number three.
And my plan is five years.
We can get through this
great, extraordinary book
in five years. We will do
about 15 classes each year.
So I think in about 75 classes
we can finish the book,
something like that.
If you have time, you should go learn it.
We could go study Chandrakirti,
and then we could go study Tsongkapa.
You know, that would be a long story.
But these five years of five courses
should give you a deep
understanding of emptiness.
And then you take that understanding
and you use it for your
Medicine Buddha practice
and you use it for your life.
Chapter three was an
investigation of the powers.
And this power means...
"Indriya" means your eye, ear
and nose, tongue, body, your sense powers,
mainly your sense powers and
also other powers of your mind.
This is one of three chapters:
chapter three, chapter four, chapter five.
They present topics
that Lord Buddha talked
about in the early stage of his teaching,
in the first turning of the wheel,
like Abhidharma, basic Abhidharma.
And it's famous that in his early years,
Buddha didn't deny anything.
He just said, let's
learn about the powers.
Let's learn about the elements.
Let's learn about the
five parts of a person.
And nowhere did he say they don't exist.
That was in the second
turning of the wheel.
So remember the three
turnings of the wheel.
First turning of the wheel:
look, you've got the sense powers,
mental powers, you've got
these five parts of a person.
And you have these other parts
of you called the elements, right?
The chemicals that make you up,
or the elemental forces that make you up.
And nowhere in the first turning
of the wheel did Lord Buddha
obviously say they didn't exist
or they were empty or something like that.
So the next three chapters
- three, four and five -
we're going to bring up three topics
that Lord Buddha covered
early in his career
in the days when he wasn't
talking about emptiness.
Then suddenly I think he
fell down and he hit his head
on a brick, and he starts saying
The Heart Sutra and The
Diamond Cutter Sutra.
Nothing exists,
and then all the students got confused.
And the whole third turning
of the wheel was the students,
confused students, asking
him what the heck's going on.
Did you hit your head or something?
So the next three chapters
treat basic Buddhist topics,
which I thought were safe,
but they're not safe.
They're also all messed up.
They're also crazy.
And that's a theme of Nargajuna.
Nargajuna wants you to understand
that there's a basic problem
with how you see the world.
There's something going on
that you don't understand.
Why?
You spend 30, 40, 50 years
trying to make your life work:
make money, have relationships,
have good health,
be a happy person.
You struggle, struggle, struggle.
And then somehow it just doesn't work.
Didn't you notice yet?
People do yoga.
I have a friend he does yoga all the time.
They're having a hip operation soon,
because the yoga messed up their hips.
And then, wait a minute,
the yoga was supposed
to make me healthy.
Yeah, I know, but it
doesn't work like that.
The mantra made me nervous.
Yeah, it happens.
Well, why doesn't it work?
Well, that's not how...
Mantra doesn't work by itself.
Mantra works because of something else.
So we're going to take the
basic, basic facts of life.
And Nargajuna says,
look, something's wrong.
People who exercise every day
go get hip surgeries.
And then there's people who
don't exercise every day,
like Pachi, who look great!
How does that work out?
What is that?
So we're trying to look into these.
Fishy. Something's fishy.
In American English,
fishy means smells bad.
And it means something's going on.
Like I just bought a cafe. Not just.
I bought a cafe almost two years ago.
And I'm supposed to go
down to the county office,
the government, local
tiny government office.
I'm supposed to ask, "Please,
I want to add a new door on the bathroom."
And then the guy signs it and
says, "Okay, add a new door."
And it's taking me almost
two years to get him
to sign the paper for the new door.
And then I start thinking,
something's fishy, you know.
Maybe this other restaurant
guy is paying him not
to give me a license. Or
maybe he wants a bribe,
I don't know what's going on.
And we say, something's fishy.
Something's fishy means
something weird is going on.
And Nargajuna says, everything's fishy.
Again, everything about
everything is fishy.
Didn't you notice that
the people who do yoga
go get hip operations.
And the people who eat all day, like Tim,
look great and thin.
Isn't there something going on here?
Do you think, maybe?
So Nargarjuna's methodology is to say,
look, something's weird.
Something doesn't work the
way you thought it worked.
Some people eat all day
and they look great.
Some people eat like
carrots all day, once a day,
and then they got this
COVID tummy to fight with.
I don't know. Something's
fishy, all right?
So chapter three, which we already covered
and it's talking about how
do the sense powers work.
Which came first, the chicken or the egg?
Which came first, the
eyeball, or colors and shapes?
And there's a big discrepancy,.
Something's fishy.
Nargajuna says, look, something's fishy.
Something's fishy about the
idea that there's a bottle
of orange liquid and
your eye. Geshe-la's eye
is already sitting on the couch
and then Geshe-la's
eye looks at the orange
and something's not right.
Something's wrong about Geshe-la's seeing.
And by the way, here we
go, if Geshe-la's eye came
before the orange juice, then
we couldn't call it an eye,
because it's not looking
at anything, okay?
It's not an eye until
it looks at something.
So you can't say Geshe-la
was sitting on the couch
with his eyes and he turned
the eyes to the orange juice
and then he saw the orange juice.
Geshe-la's eyes were working
before the orange juice was there.
You can't say that. Why?
It's not an eye to elicit something.
If it's an eye before
it looks at something,
then your nose is also an eye,
because it doesn't look
at something either.
Okay, it just doesn't make sense.
I'll say it again.
And Nargajuna, you got
to say it like 10 times.
Was Geshe-la's eye on the couch
before he looked at the orange color?
And Nargajuna says, no, are you crazy?
And you say, no, no, I was on the couch
and then I picked up the orange.
Come on, you're saying your eye was an eye
before you held up the orange?
Yeah, the eye was waiting
and then the orange came.
Yeah, well what's an eye?
An eye is something that sees things.
But it wasn't seeing anything
before you picked up an orange though.
So it wasn't an eye, don't you get it?
But then after you picked up the orange,
the eye's already gone.
Duh, the orange came,
there must've been an eye
after you saw the orange
the eye was already,
let's put it this way:
The orange made the eye a seer.
So the orange came first.
The orange came first,
then the eye came later.
Yeah, but if the eye wasn't
there yet, who saw the orange?
Nargajuna says, don't you get it?
Something weird is going on.
All those yoga guys are
getting hip operations.
All those people doing Medicine
Buddha mantras all day,
they're also getting sick.
What's going on?
And he's asking us to think about it,
starting with your eye.
Chapter four, I mean one of
the first great teachings
of the Buddha is the
five parts of a person,
the five heaps. Right?
So there's five parts to you: your body,
your capacity of feeling, your
capacity of discrimination,
all the other parts about
you, all the other stuff.
All the other parts of Tim.
That's like me, I try not to
sneeze too when I'm sleeping,
so V doesn't get wake up.
Okay anyway. And fifthly, your
mind, you're raw awareness.
So look, Buddha never said,
Nargajuna, that they were empty.
sS what's that all about?
You say they're empty.
And then Nargajuna says, look,
if I discuss the five heaps,
the five parts to you,
it would take a year.
Let's just talk about
your physical body, okay?
First part. Pachi's arm, Pachi's ear,
you know, Rebecca's nose.
Let's talk about your physical.
In the fourth chapter, which is called,
"An Investigation of the
Five Parts of a Person",
he doesn't bother
investigating four of them.
He says, let's get your body straight
and then we can talk about the rest.
We got this lady looking at her arm.
The causes that made her arm,
which you can say is skin
or chemicals in the skin,
they weren't causes
until the arm was there.
You can't call something
a cause until the result.
When you see a result, you
can say something is a cause.
Oh, look, somebody got better.
What was the cause?
They were doing mantras,
Medicine Buddha mantras.
But you can't talk about the
causes of good health as causes
until the good health comes.
Therefore they must be the same time.
If you do a mantra to stop cancer,
then before you finish the first mantra,
the cancer should go away,
if things work like that.
So he's said, look, try
to understand the things
that made your arm didn't make your arm,
because it's not until the arm is there
that you can say they were causes.
Until the result comes you
can't call something a cause.
Until smoke comes, you can't
say there's a fire there.
You can't.
The smoke indicates the fire.
The arm indicates the causes of the arm.
Until the arm is created by
the chemicals in the skin,
you can't call the chemicals
in the skin causes of the arm,
because there's no arm yet.
And if the arm's not there
yet, the result's not there.
If the result's not there yet,
you can't call anything
causes of the result,
because the result
doesn't have causes yet.
So that's the fourth chapter.
If you feel confused, you're
in the right place, okay?
If you're starting to doubt your mantras,
you're in the right place.
You should doubt your mantras.
Come on, didn't you notice
not everyone who says,
Medicine Buddha mantras have
been said for 2000 years.
All those people died. Duh.
Then there must be something else going on
and there must be something
else that makes the mantra work.
By the way, not all those people died,
probably a lot of them didn't
die, but we don't see it.
We can't see it.
All right, Chapter number five.
"An Investigation of the Elements".
And these are SA, CHU, ME, RLUNG,
you know, earth, water, fire, wind.
And you know, it's very common to say,
oh, here's fire by the way.
There's fire in her hands
that help create her hands.
And then she's also feeling the fire.
And these are not some
stupid Ayurvedic thing
from 2000 years ago.
It's not like that.
For example, nowadays in physics,
we would call it inertia,
or gravity, or bonding forces.
These are the elemental forces.
It's not that Nargajuna
thought there was some fire
inside your arm or something like that.
And by the way, Nargajuna
was a master of the elements.
He was an Alchemist.
He was famous for making gold.
He got in trouble for making
gold, which is a long story.
He knew how chemicals work.
He knew how the elements work.
And he knew the basic forces of physics,
the forces that bond things together,
the forces that tear things apart.
He understood them, gravity and
inertia, he understood them.
So if there are certain forces
that are underneath
everything, if this bottle cap
has some fire in it, if
it has some temperature,
it's not an absolute zero, right?
So it has some temperature.
It also has some fluidity.
It can stretch a little bit.
It has water.
It has fire.
If it has those things,
well, which came first?
And by the way, it's here
in the "Investigation of the Elements",
that Nargajuna really gets
into: How do you define things?
How do you decide something is a fire?
Well, what's your definition of fire?
I say fire is an energy that causes heat
and is typified by burning.
and it's typified by
the burning of things.
That's what I say.
That's a definition of fire.
What?
What's the definition of fire?
TSA ZHING SREG PA
in Tibetan, quickly ,you
say hot and burning.
Okay, so which came first, the definition
or the thing you want to define?
Well, the thing you want to
define has to come first,
otherwise you don't know
what you're defining.
I wasn't talking about bananas,
I was talking about fire.
Well okay, tell me what
you want to define first.
Okay, bananas, fire,
what's your definition?
Hot and burning.
Which came first?
Fire.
Which came second?
Hot and burning.
How can you have fire
without hot and burning?
Are you crazy?
Come on, the definition came first.
Then the thing came, hot
and fire, hot and burning.
Then you say what you're
defining: bananas.
No, but Geshe-la there's no
connection between banana,
and hot and burning.
Well, there's no connection between fire,
It's just a word.
So, you can't even define the things
that make up the bottom
that you're sitting on.
So how can you use Medicine
Buddha mantras? Come on.
How are you going to use a mantra?
Chapter six.
Don't forget, we're trying
to review eight chapters
that we had already and
really, if you try to start
with me on course three of
Nargajuna at chapter nine,
if you try to start there without doing
the first eight chapters,
you're going to get more confused.
But anyway, it'll be fun.
By the way, in the monastery,
confusion is a technique.
Confusion is a technique.
And it's recognized as a technique.
The teacher will sit down, say,
let's see, it's like December,
let me confuse my students today.
And the goal of the
teacher at that moment,
is that nobody in the class
knows what's going on.
And then they all get frustrated
and they'll work harder, or they'll quit.
So you can get rid of
the not serious students
and save time.
And then the serious students
are going to work harder
because they're so frustrated and angry,
because they don't understand anything.
So confusion is a tool
of the great Buddhist
teachers like Nargajuna.
So if you get confused, it's on purpose..
If you don't get confused,
it's because I gave a good explanation.
Chapter six is an investigation, pariksha,
of desire and who feels the desire.
Let's talk about desire
and who feels the desire.
And by the way, by now
you should be smelling
or feeling that there's,
in English we say, a method
to Nargajuna's madness.
He is not just throwing
out topics randomly.
Now you're a third of
the way through this book
and you should start asking yourself:
What's the connection between this chapter
and the last chapter?
It seems like Nargajuna is
jumping around like crazy.
And Geshe-la and Choney Lama
took you through the logic
of all 27 chapters in the first
course. So don't complain.
It's not that Nargajuna is jumping around
to different topics.
He has a plan.
To try to see his master
plan is a great achievement.
If you can get a feeling
for Nargajuna's master plan
for "Wisdom", then really you're starting
to understand how mantra works.
So the picture here is,
I tried to find a picture
of desire and this is the
one that Geshe-la has.
It's a desire for churros,
or пончик (ponchik),
or 油条 (yóutiáo), or doughnut.
By the way, I didn't find a
good donut shop in Sedona.
The best one in the universe
is in the Guadalajara Airport.
Where is it? You got it?
I might have to move to West Sedona.
Okay, anyway, so which comes first,
the desire or the person who feels it?
That girl has desire for the doughnut.
So who came first,
the girl or the desire?
She's a girl who desires.
So can we call her a girl who
desires before she has desire?
No, you cannot.
Do you have to wait until
after she has the desire
to call her a girl with desire?
Yeah, you do.
Okay, so what made her desire?
What is she desiring about?
It's a doughnut.
So the doughnut has to come
before the girl, right?
Like before the girls born,
the doughnut should come.
Why?
Beause she doesn't have desire
until the doughnut is there.
The doughnut has to be there first.
Then you can have a girl
who wants a doughnut.
So by definition, you
got to have a doughnut
before you have the
girl who has the desire
for the doughnut, right?
Right.
But the girl can't desire the doughnut
until the girl's there,
so the doughnut has
to come after the girl.
Come on, try to get it.
Try to understand what's going on.
How can the girl desire a doughnut
if the doughnut's not there?
If the doughnut's already there,
how can you have a girl desire a doughnut?
And if you have a girl
who desires a doughnut,
the doughnut must come first.
But if the girl doesn't come first,
then how can there be a
doughnut that she has desire.
She should feel desire.
She should have mental
afflicitons in her mind.
And then she sees a doughnut
and the mental affliction wakes up, right?
So which came first?
That's chapter six.
Chapter seven, this is called
"An Investigation of Starting,
Staying and Stopping".
And the other guy says,
look, if things start,
then they're not empty.
If things stay, then they're not empty.
If things stop, then they're not empty.
Why?
Beause they have causes.
How can they say they're
empty if things don't start?
If things don't start,
how can they be empty?
If things start, how can they be empty?
Empty means nothing about
them, but they have causes.
They must have causes,
or they can't start.
Causes must be inherent in
a thing for it to start,
because a thing can't start without causes
and especially desire cannot
start without its causes.
So desire must have its causes.
Therefore, desire is not empty.
Nargajuna said everything
is empty, but it's not. Why?
It has an inherent thing.
What's the inherent thing?
It doesn't happen until it has it causes
that it's inherent in that thing.
Desire cannot come up
unless the causes come up.
That girl's not going to feel desire,
I don't know, for a punch in the nose.
There has to be something nice there,
then you can have desire for it.
There has to be a seed,
then you can have it.
We're looking at a foot of a person
about to run a race.
And where did the race start?
When did the race start?
Was it when they shot the gun?
Or was it the first part
of the gunshot noise,
or the second part of the gunshot noise?
Or was it the final part
of the gunshot noise
and then the gunshot went
off, and then the people ran?
So where did the race start?
And you cannot find a place
where the race started.
You think this guy's at the starting line,
but there is no starting line.
Look, his fingers on the starting line,
or not on the starting line?
And how far between the
finger and the starting line?
What about the other side
of the starting line?
Where's the starting line?
And Nargajuna says, come
on, something's fishy.
Chapter eight,
"An Investigation of Agents and Actions".
Doers and things that they do.
Let's investigate doers and
the things that they do.
Well what's the big example Geshe-la?
Karma.
If there's no me, if there's no Michael,
then who makes the karma
if there's no Michael?
If there's no me and mine,
Nargajuna, then there's no karma.
Why?
Beause Michael has to
be there to make karma.
So according to you,
what? There's no karma?
Why?
There's no, Michael.
I didn't say there's no Michael.
You did say there's no Michael.
You say Michael never started.
Did Michael come without starting?
Yeah, and Nargajuna says,
you can't find this starting.
Okay, then there's no Michael.
Okay! There's no Michael.
Well then there's no karma, okay?
Yeah, there's no karma.
Well then why did you
bow down at the Buddha
who taught karma at the first verse?
Why, you crazy?
And by the way, I'm not, it's not BS.
It's deep.
It's important.
If you understand it,
your mantras will work.
And if you don't understand it,
maybe you get a little
power out of mantra,
because of your faith, but
you won't get the full power.
You'll get like one millionth of 1% power
on the mantras if you don't
understand how they work.
How does a mantra work?
How does karma work?
How does action work?
When did the action start?
Who did the action?
What action did they start?
When did the action start?
Did the person doing
the action come first,
or the action came first?
If the action didn't come
before the person who did the action,
how can you call the
person who did the action
a person who did the action,
because there's no action yet?
Something's fishy.
And it's not just crazy talk.
There's a reason why this
book survived for 2,000 years.
And there's a reason
why hundreds of people,
hundreds of great people,
wrote commentaries.
There's a reason.
There's something
important about this book.
Now, last thing.
Oh by the way, we have a mom
and a daughter baking a cake.
The mom and the daughter
who are making a cake,
are they bakers right now?
No, they're not bakers,
nothing's been baked yet.
Give me a break.
They're not bakers.
They're just people with weird hats on.
They're not bakers yet.
There's nothing baked.
Until there's something baked,
you can't call them a baker.
Got it?
But how can you have a baked
thing without the baker?
If the girl and her mom cannot be bakers
until the cake is baked,
because until then there's no
reason to call them bakers.
But the cake can't bake itself.
Somebody has to come and bake the cake.
So the baker has to come before the cake.
No, no, no, I just told
you. The baker can't come
before the cake, because
the baker's not a baker
until they bake something.
Yeah, but I just told you
if they bake something,
there's got to be someone
to bake it before that.
There has to be a baker
before baked cake, right?
No, no, no. You can't have
a baker before a baked cake,
because until you have a baked
cake the baker's not a baker,
because the baker didn't bake anything.
And it's not a joke.
And if you're going to
use Medicine Buddha mantra
to stop cancer, then you
got to understand this.
Which word in the mantra fixed the cancer,
the first one or the last one?
And which mantra was it,
number 10,000, or number 9,000?
Which mantra worked?
When did it work?
What do you mean mantra?
There is no mantra till something happens,
otherwise it's just a sentence.
You know, you can say banana
and if nothing happens,
it's not a mantra.
You can say OM MANI PADME HUM
and if it doesn't do anything,
then it's not a mantra.
A mantra does some miracle thing.
Until there's a miracle,
you can't have a mantra.
But if a miracle doesn't happen,
you can't have a mantra either.
Got it?
Now last thing we have a few minutes left.
This "Wisdom" text of Nargajuna
is a great place to
learn a little Sanskrit.
I call it, you know, what's it called?
Get to know Sanskrit, or something.
So if you want to learn some Sanskrit,
which is what you're going to talk
after you become a Buddha,
so you better work on it now.
Let's learn a little Sanskrit.
This is the perfect book.
The verses are short, sweet.
If you want to learn Sanskrit,
in the monastery they'd say,
oh just memorize the book.
It's not that hard.
If you get in the habit of
memorizing, you can memorize.
,GANG GIS RTEN CING 'BREL BAR 'BYUNG,
,'GAG PA MED PA SKYE MED PA,
,CHAD PA MED PA RTAG MED PA,
,'GRO MED PA 'ONG BA MED,
,THA DAD DON MIN DON GCIG MIN,
,RDZOGS PA'I SANGS RGYAS SMRA RNAMS KYI,
,DAM PA DE LA PHYAG 'TSAL
LO,, or something like that...
You can memorize it.
You can do it.
So let's learn a few Sanskrit words.
And here's the Sanskrit
words that we already learned
in the first eight chapters.
Okay, Tim, you got it for me?
We're going to get to know Sanskrit.
And the first word you should
learn is the name of the book.
And it's very embarrassing
for your teacher
when somebody asks you,
what are you studying?
You say, I don't know,
but I've been doing it for three years.
Then Geshe-la feels embarrassed.
So what book are you studying?
Prajna. Say Prajna.
- [All] Prajna.
- [Michael] Prajna.
- So the J is not an
English J, it's a D-Z.
The Russians are right.
It's na, prajna, prajna.
And then there's a long A.
The last A is a long A.
The Tibetan is SHES RAB.
It's a little bit of an E sound, SHES RAB.
You don't say sharob. SHES RAB, SHES RAB.
The Sanskrit word, we're going to learn
to deconstruct a Sanskrit word.
We're going to learn how to
break down a Sanskrit word
into its parts.
And then we're going to learn cognates,
which is?
(speaking off microphone)
Yeah, related modern words.
So pra- means to come in front.
It comes in the English
words, proud, prow of a boat,
the front of a boat, forward.
So pra- means in front,
it becomes like supra,
super, super good, super good.
Okay, so pra- here means supra.
And supra comes from pra-.
Then we have the root.
When you see that little
square root sign (√),
it means a Sanskrit root
√jna and that means to know.
And that's why there's a K
in the English word, know,
because there used to be a
jna, jna and that came in
to the English word
know, or gnostic, or ken.
You know, is it beyond your ken or not,
meaning your understanding.
So √jna means to know.
The Russians, you've got
the perfect verb, Знаю (,
Я Знаю (Ya Znayu).
Russian is much closer
to the original Sanskrit,
because it's closer to Greek.
Last thing to say about wisdom,
it has a feminine ending,
long A, prajna, prajna.
And generally wisdom is
considered a feminine aspect
because it gives birth to
all kinds of good things.
Let's do one more Sanskrit word
and we're done with the class. Yay!
I'm sorry the classes are so long
and I'm not sorry you should sit there.
Okay, say pariksha.
- [All] pariksha.
- Pariksha.
So that means an investigation.
And you know, you got to know this word
if you're going to read
the 27 investigations,
the 27 chapters of the
book called, "Wisdom".
The book called "Prajna" has 27 parikshas.
Pari- means all around,
like the perimeter.
Generally A in Sanskrit
becomes an E in English.
So pari- becomes peri- like
perimeter or periscope.
So when you get in a
submarine and you look
all around the ocean,
it's called a periscope.
Pari-, all around.
Iksha means to see.
It's an ancient verb, to look.
And there's a German word
auge, which comes from that.
And then that came into English as ocular
and even the word eye. So the
word eye comes from iksha.
The eyeball comes from,
eye comes from auge,
comes from iksha, which means to look.
So when you look all around something,
that's an investigation,
a pari- iksh, pariksha.
Okay, so we're going to pariksha.
So try to learn those few Sanskrit words.
So far, we have prajna, wisdom,
the name of Nargajuna's great book
and pariksha, which is
crucial for the book.
It's an investigation of different ideas.
We are investigating, especially,
why does the Medicine Buddha mantra work.
And if you want it to
work better, or stronger,
then understand its emptiness.
Try to understand its emptiness.
If you really understand its emptiness,
the mantra can make you into a
being who can jump from world
to world in a few
seconds, planet to planet,
in a few seconds and help
billions of people each time.
If you really understand
the emptiness of the mantra,
it can make you a Buddha.
Okay, cool. See you in the next class
and we'll start our new chapter, nine.